<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="op-ed">Don’t Just Thank Black Women. Follow Us.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>The New York Times, 16 December 2017</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <author>Angela Peoples</author>
            <p>Angela Peoples is the founder and principal strategist of the political consulting group MsPeoples.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div>
           <head>
           <p>Don’t Just Thank Black Women. Follow Us.</p>
           </head>
           <p>By Angela Peoples</p>
           <p>Dec. 16, 2017</p>
           <p>When I joined the 470,000 other women who walked down <placeName>Constitution
             Avenue</placeName> toward the <placeName>National Mall</placeName> on <event>Jan. 21, the day after <persName type="politician">Donald Trump’s</persName> inauguration</event>,
              I carried a sign saying, “Don’t Forget, <rs type="race-gender">White Women</rs> Voted for Trump.”</p>
           <p>My message stood in stark contrast to the theme of togetherness that dominated the
             <event>Women’s March</event> — the pink <objectName>“pussy hats”</objectName> and “girl power” placards, and chants about
             how women would lead the resistance. This was exactly the point. I made the sign to
             communicate that in a world where 53 percent of <rs type="race-gender">white women</rs> voters chose a racist,
             elitist sexual predator for president, the idea that we all want the same thing is a myth.</p>
           <p>The point wasn’t to antagonize the <event>Women’s March</event> participants, who were mostly
             white. Rather, I wanted to highlight that on a national level, <rs type="race-gender">white women</rs> are not
              unified in opposition to Trumpism and can’t be counted on to fight it. Instead, it’s
              the identity, experience and leadership of <rs type="race-gender">black women</rs> that we must look to.</p>
           <p>Democrats want to position themselves as a pro-woman, pro-immigrant, pro-equality
             party. We do ourselves a disservice if we believe the myth that a majority of white
             women voting in the era of Trump are moved by that message. The numbers don’t lie:
             For many <rs type="race-gender">white women</rs>, it’s racial identity, not gender or party, that guides their
              choices in the voting booth. As my sign pointed out, in 2016 more than half of white
              female voters chose Mr. Trump. A year later, in <placeName>Virginia</placeName>, 51 percent of <rs type="race-gender">white women</rs>
              voted for the Republican <persName type="politician">Ed Gillespie</persName>, who lost after running an anti-immigrant,
              white-nationalist-sympathizing, <persName>Steve Bannon</persName>-backed campaign for governor.</p>
           <p>Last week, by late Tuesday evening, we learned that two-thirds of <rs type="race-gender">white female</rs>
             voters in <placeName>Alabama</placeName> had once again voted for the Trump agenda, casting ballots for
             <persName type="politician">Roy Moore</persName>, a man accused of sexually assaulting teenagers and one with a dismal
             record on civil rights who was on tape saying the country was last “great” during slavery.</p>
           <p>Despite this, the Democratic candidate, <persName type="politician">Doug Jones</persName>, was able to score an unlikely
             victory thanks to the historic turnout of black voters — specifically, <rs type="race-gender">black women</rs>.
             A full 98 percent cast ballots for Mr. Jones. Ninety-eight percent.</p>
           <p>If I had to make another sign after the Alabama election, it would say this:
             “Bet on <rs type="race-gender">black women</rs>. Follow <rs type="race-gender">black women</rs>. Give power to <rs type="race-gender">black women</rs>.” I’d wave
             it in front of the headquarters of the Democratic National Committee and every
             political start-up’s office, and pass out copies to all those emerging resistance groups.</p>
           <p>At a time when others are clinging to or are willing to tolerate political messages
             rooted in white nationalism and fear, <rs type="race-gender">black women</rs> are the voters who’ve consistently
             rejected these things. We’re keenly aware that issues that affect us and our communities
             are always on the ballot, whether it’s access to lifesaving health care, the fight to
             save public schools, or the imminent threat of police violence and harassment. We
             know we don’t have the option to sit out elections.</p>
           <p>It’s our insight here that Democrats should look to. The issues about which we’re
             informed and passionate affect Americans of all races and genders, even if others
             may not use their votes as wisely as we do.</p>
           <p>We don’t just vote; we lead as well by mobilizing our communities to vote. In
             <placeName>Alabama</placeName>, leaders like <persName>Lenice C. Emanuel</persName> of the <orgName>Alabama Institute for Social Justice</orgName>
             and <persName>Felecia Lucky</persName> of the <orgName>Black Belt Community Foundation</orgName> spent years building the
             infrastructure that led to Tuesday night’s victory. In <event>Virginia</event>, projects like In Charge:
             <orgName><rs type="race-gender">Black Women</rs> Taking Action</orgName> tapped into the turnout power of <rs type="race-gender">black women</rs> to engage over 300
             black female volunteers and contact nearly 5,000 voters in the final three weeks before <event>Election Day</event>.</p>
           <p><orgName>BlackPAC</orgName>, led by <persName>Adrianne Shropshire</persName>, was on the ground before the elections in <placeName>Virginia</placeName>
             and in <placeName>Alabama</placeName>, with an army of canvassers. Other groups led by <rs type="race-gender">black women</rs>, like the
             <orgName>Movement for Black Lives Electoral Project</orgName>, <orgName>Woke Vote</orgName> and <orgName>Southerners on New Ground</orgName>,
             do this work across the country and need support.</p>
           <p>Instead of taking this political talent, enthusiasm and energy for granted — and
             instead of wasting energy on white voters who don’t share its values — the Democratic
             Party should invest in amplifying <rs type="race-gender">black women’s</rs> proven dedication to the party.
             As a first step, perhaps some would-be candidates who think of themselves as “next in line”
             should step aside and make space for more <rs type="race-gender">black women</rs> like <persName type="politician">Tishaura Jones</persName> in <placeName>St. Louis</placeName> and
             <persName type="politician">Stacey Abrams</persName> in <placeName>Georgia</placeName>.</p>
           <p><rs type="race-gender">Black women</rs> are being widely credited for saving the day in <placeName>Alabama</placeName>,
             and that credit is one small step in the right direction. But we don’t need thanks —
             we need you to get out of the way and follow our lead.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
